Guide to the Sacred Heart Church records 1916-1994 (Bulk 1982-1994) CPAA 04-02
Central Connecticut State University, Publisher
Sacred Heart Church records1916-1994, (Bulk 1982-1994)
CPAA 04-02
1 box (1 linear ft.)
Central Connecticut State University
Sacred Heart Church (New Britain, Conn.)
Material in this collection relates to Sacred Heart church, the oldest Polish American parish in New Britain Connecticut, established in 1894. It was an ethnic parish lead by the very powerful Monsignor Lucyan Bojnowski who was was a very influential figure not only for parishioners’ lives but the entire town. Paul Wysocki, served as pastor of the parish during the years 1977-2003. These years were very important to the ethnic parish. In the 1980’s a new wave of political immigrants came to the city from Poland (a result of Solidarity immigration) and wanted to participate and to receive services they were used to in Poland. However, some actions created frictions between the old and the new Polonia. There were questions of church financial contributions, ownership of the church, and who should make or advice pastors on changes within the parish. This collection concentrates on the post solidarity immigrants and controversies within the church from the 1980’s till mid 1990’s.
Provenance
Part of the material that is restricted was given to the archives by Prof. Daniel S. Buczek in 2004 with restriction on access for the 10 years, therefore collection will be available for full research in 2014. Prof.Buczek had written a book on the history of Sacred Heart titled: People of God: a centennial history of Sacred Heart of Jesus Parish, New Britain, Connecticut. Second part of the material was given to the archives in January 2008 without any restrictions.
Access Restrictions
Open for research with some restrictions. Part of the material in the collection is restricted and sealed till 2014. Two scrapbooks and folders related to Sacred Heart cemetery controversy in mid 1980’s is available and open for research.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Sacred Heart church is the oldest Polish American parish in New Britain Connecticut, established in 1894. It was an ethnic parish lead by the very powerful Monsignor Lucyan Bojnowski who was a very influential figure not only for parishioners’ lives but influenced the entire town. Paul Wysocki served as pastor of the parish during the years 1977-2003.
Scope and Content Note
Collection consists of two sealed envelopes with restricted material related to church controversy during Rev. Paul Wysocki's appointment as a Pastor of the Sacred Heart church in New Britain, Connecticut. Remaining folders are related to a cemetery controversy, consisting of correspondence with church officials and attorneys for the defendant Paul Wysocki and the plaintiff the Grygorcewicz family. Material covers years 1983-1994. Two scrapbooks contain variety of material related to the church, immigrants in New Britain area and previous pastors of the church that cover years from 1916 till 1994.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Inventory
Access Points
Subject Names:
Bojnowski, Lucyan, 1888-1960.
Subject Organizations:
Sacred Heart Church (New Britain, Conn.)
Subject Topics:
Polish-Americans – New Britain – Connecticut.; Catholic Church – Clergy.
Document Types:
Scrapbook.; Clippings.
Related Material
For the history of the Sacred Heart Church see the book written by Prof. Daniel S. Buczek entitled People of God: a centennial history of Sacred Heart of Jesus Parish. For additional information please see collection of anniversary pamphlets located at the archives.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Inventory
  - Sacred Heart church - information related to helping immigrants, 1979-1987; school tuition payment 1984-87. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sacred Heart church controversy related documents from the committee, archbishop letter, and assistant priest, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sacred Heart church cemetery controversy, Grygorcewicz family vs. Rev. Paul Wysocki, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sacred Heart church controversy - related correspondence, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Portrait of a man 8 page long typed unsigned letter of testimony to a good character of Rev. Wysocki. [after August, 1987]; Obituary of Rev. Paul Wysocki. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook., 1982-1988; Newspaper clippings related to controversies of the parish pastor Rev. Paul Wysocki.Clipping are arranged in chronological order in one binder. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook., 1916-1984; Newspaper clippings, extracts from parish anniversary pamphlets, Federal Writer's Project interviews related to Poles in New Britain, information on parochial school and its history, bulk of material related to Rev. Bojnowski. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sacred Heart church records, undated; restricted until 2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sacred Heart church records, undated; restricted until 2014 (Box 1, Folder 9)